[MUSIC]
Well, hello.
In this video we're going to play with the
Android emulator and I'm
going to show you, uh, some tips and tricks that we can do with it.
But, uh, first of all let's just have a bit of
fun. We've got two of them running,
so why don't we send a message from one to the other.
Ah, let's start, uh, messaging, on this emulator.
Okay.
And, uh, we'll write a new message.
Okay, so to, who should we send it to?
Well, for this, we need to know the, uh, how to send it to
the other emulator, and the trick to know
is that, uh, we're going to
use this number up here in the title bar,
so you'll see that
we have the name of the emulator instance
but also this number—this 5554.
In fact the
first emulator that you start will always
have the number
5554. Ah, the second emulator will have two more than that, so 5556.
The third emulator h-if we had a third one
running, would be 5558, etcetera.
You can have up to 16 emulators.
I've never run 16 at a time, but I'm sure
someone in this course will tr-will try to.
So, let's, uh, send a message
to 5554, and we will say, "Hi," okay, right,
"let me out
I'm an emulator," or something like that.
So we'll click the Send button.
Okay, so this number, this 5554, is a port
number.
Now what is a port?
Well, just like, uh, when you dock
a ship at a port, it's a way for us
to connect to, uh, programs which are
running on a computer.
Ah, okay, let's start this up.
Oh, look, we have a message.
There we go.
So we have a message from 5556, the other
emulator.
And we could respond to that, and, uh, so-and text message, uh, each emulator for free.
Uh, so, the next segment
I'm going to show you is that, uh, the emulator, in addition to supporting the, uh,
keep the hardware keypads over here, so,
here we are; we have some buttons like
the home menu, ect-the home, for example.
Um, we can also control, uh, whether the emulator is in landscape or portrait.
So, uh, let's do that.
So on a, this Mac I'm going to press
Ctrl and F11.
Ah-ha!
And it's flipped over, and it, uh, restarts the home screen, ah, in its, ah, landscape mode.
Now, why is that useful?
Well, the answer is that, behind the
scenes, um, when a phone call
comes in or when the user flips the phone
over to its side,
uh, the system does quite a bit of work and
your app may have to
do quite a bit of work as well.
Perhaps it has a different layout, uh, ah,
configuration.
And so being able to test it on the
emulator,
uh, is an important part of getting your app
ready for publishing.
Right, so we can flip it back.
Ah, ah, one surprise, uh, I had
was that, uh, you've got to release both the
Ctrl key and F-F11 for this to work.
Uh, I'm holding down the Ctrl key
now and pressing it multiple times does
nothing.
It, it, it ignores the function key until
I let go of, uh, both the Ctrl key and F11.
So if you're wondering why it's not
working, why it
can't flip, make sure that you let go of
both.
Okay.
Let's pop it back.
Now there are other keys as well, and I'll
show
you later on in this video the, the link
for that.
Uh, right now,
uh, let's, um, show you the secret, uh, the, uh, secret way into the emulator.
Um,and for that we are going to need to
connect to this, uh, port number, this 5556.
Uh, and then we can start talking to the
secret
interface, if you like of the, of the
emulator.
For this, uh, we'll use a, uh, an old tool called, uh, Telnet,
uh, which allows us to type commands directly, uh, and connect
to a particular port on a certain machine.
Right, so, on a Mac how do we do that?
Well, first of all we will start a terminal,
okay.
Ah, so this is our terminal instance.
And I can now type telnet, and connect to
somewhere.
For example, let's have some fun, let's
connect to the BBC.
Hey, BBC,
bbc.co.uk.
And if I was a, uh, web browser
like Firefox, Safari, Internet Explorer,
by default I would connect to port 80.
So let's connect to port 80 on that
machine.
So, I've now connected to a distant
machine over in the UK, and here's where I
would request a particular webpage, um, so I would, there we go.
Uh, I was not fast enough; let's try it again.
Uh, let's connect here and, type some
gibberish.
And I guess what the, the server, uh, the BBC server did not
like my, my, my gibberish and said, hah, I
do not understand.
So it, um, it responded with, "Hey 400, bad
request"
and sent—the client sent a bad request and
closed the connection on us.
Um, so if we were a more polite, uh, web client, we would of
course, uh, would've sent the correct, uh, codes to request a particular, uh, web page,
and we would, and the server would have sent back information, or sent
back, uh, an image, or sent back the text of the web page.
Uh, right, now we've finished, uh, playing at the BBC;
Let's, uh, connect to the, ah, emulator.
For this we need to know where it is and
which port number.
Uh, so it, it's, uh, on the local host so, I do telnet space localhost and Port 80.
But wait, what if you are a Windows user,
ah, how do you get, ah, telnet?
Well for that you might start by googling, uh, How to start telnet on Windows.
And, uh, here's a web query I performed
earlier; here it is.
And you discover that on Windows 7 and
Windows 8, uh, you have to jump through
some hoops first to reinstall, uh, telnet.
It's no longer available by default.
And here's the steps you'll need to go
through.
You'll need to open the Control Panel,
ah, find Programs and Features, and, and then look for Windows Features,
ah, and then, fe-, inside Windows Features you'll find a checkbox for the Telnet Client.
So, clicking on that will af-, and then
clicking on OK, will re-install, ah, ah,
Telnet client for you.
Right, so now you've got telnet, um, what do
you need to do to start it? Um, I-, you
have a Start menu, uh, enter Cmd,
so this is, uh, Windows equivalent of me typing, uh, terminal
in my Mac. And once you're inside the, ah,
command
window, ah, you can type telnet.
Now these instructions suggest just you
simply press Enter, but, uh, rather than do
that, ah, you could actually, ah, specify the, uh, machine that you want
to connect to and the port number, as we did over
here.
So, we are going to connect now to, uh, it's, uh,
there we go, uh, local host port 80.
Right, so let's do this.
Um, but we don't want port 80.
We want a different port.
We want to connect to the emulator, so
let's connect to, uh,
either 5554, the first emulator instance,
or my second emulator instance 5556.
Here we go.
All right.
We are in.
We are connected.
I'm now talking to, uh, the emulator.
I'm talking to the Android console that's, uh, behind this emulator.
And, uh, very helpfully it provides a little help menu so
I can type help and get a list of
commands.
Uh, so one of the useful commands is, uh, I could, uh, send a text message, an SMS
message, so let's send an SMS message to, ah, this Android instance, and
we'll say this message is from, let's say,
787, and we'll say Hello Emulator.
Woops.
I didn't get the syntax right.
Well, we forgot to send,
ah, sms send,
and then we need to say who it's from, so
787 blah blah blah.
And we'll say, Hello!
Okay.
Back on this side we'll see at the top
here we get, a little message appeared at
the top.
And if I pull this down,
there it is,
I've got it there.
Okay, let's pull it down.
I've got my little hello message.
All
right
So now I could write and test apps that
respond to text messages and test them
inside the emulator.
Uh, I can also from, uh this con-, this, the console, ah, control what
the emulator thinks the battery level is
doing, so right now,
it thinks it's at 50%, and over here,
after that
message disappears, you'll see it's, uh,
showing that it's connected.
It's recharging, and it's
recharging from 50%.
So let's, um, change that.
Right, so I will do help power, and we can
do power change the capacity to say zero.
Ah, okay, and you'll see now in our little
window, absolute, oh, okay.
Message disappears that it's actually
recharging from zero.
Ah, so again, we could, uh, test our apps
easily which respond to power messages.
Another useful thing we can do here is to
change the window scale.
So if I do help window, we'll see that we
have one command called scale, so let's
make it a smaller window, say 0.5.
And we have a little window somewhere.
Where have you gone.
There.
Uh, you can try to make the scale, ah, larger.
In practice I've found this is, a, a, ,a, a easy way and fast way to crash
the emulator. Uh, and then one final thing which I've, uh, often
used is the, the avd command to
temporarily pause the execution.
So, um, in avd, you'll see there's a start and stop
command, so I can do avd stop, and this has
paused, uh, the emulator, so it's not going to respond to any events right now.
Uh, this is, uh, useful if I'm running my laptop without power, and
this cuts the amount of power used by the
emulator by about half.
It's still using some CPU power, even
though we've, we've asked it to stop.
Um, but it's a useful trick if you're, if
you're trying to
make your, your own actual laptop battery
run for as long as
possible and you don't want to quit the
emulator.
Okay, so let's, uh, start it again.
Okay, you'll also notice there's a
snapshot interface there
and you can use that to, uh, save snapshots and, uh, d-, list snapshots.
Uh, this is a way so you can, ah, restart your emulater instance from
a particular known state, perhaps, uh, with a couple of applications already installed.
That kind of thing.
This is, this is kind
of fun.
Let's, uh, let's, uh, let's call our, our emulator. So, into
the gsm menu, discover that we can [laughs] call it.
So all right. Hey, well, we better give it
a number that we're calling from, so there
we go.
And. [pause]
Our phone, somebody's calling our
emulator.
Unfortunately the emulator doesn't, ah, fully support voice calls,
and we can't make real outgoing calls, but
again, this a way to be able to test our
apps that might respond to calls.
Also, Android will, um, pull the rug out from
underneath running applications when the
phone is running.
Ah, a lo-, a lot of behind the scenes works.
Ah, a lot of behind the scenes functionality
happens that the user doesn't realize
where and
the Android operating system will
temporarily put an app
on ice, if you like, and then restore it
later,
um, just in the same way that on a stage, ah, the
actors might disappear during the interval
and then when we pull
back the curtain again all of the actors
are back in
places, and the scenery is back, and the
props are ready.
Ah, Android does the same thing with apps in
order
to manage the very limited resources that
a phone has.
Okay, so, uh, let, we'll cancel the call, um, right.
And we need to give it the number again,
6754321.
Ha, and we hung up on the emulator.
Okay, so that's it for now; you've watched
me play with the emulator.
Now it's time for you to, to learn how to
use these emulators, so, um, let's see.
I, go to Google Chrome.
I want to show you two things on
the, um, developer website.
Uh, first of all is, uh, where can I
find the instructions for the, the
keyboard shortcuts.
Uh, they're not immediately obvious.
They are actually just a, a little lower than
you might expect.
Here I am on the developer.android.com,
and, um, the
last section on the left, uh, left here is, um,
we've
gone down past Download, we've gone past Workflows, we're past Support
Library. Inside Tools Help, uh you'll find in
here the emulator.
And this lists the keyboard shortcuts, uh, that you can use.
And like I say, the most useful one I find
has been
the ability to swap between different
layout orientations, either the portrait
or landscape.
So, uh, make sure you practice that,
and also see if, uh, full screen,
Alt+Enter works on your system as well.
And finally, let's, uh, talk about the speed of the eliminator and what
you can do to speed it up on your system.
So, um, if you're lucky you will be able
to get the, uh, Intel accelerator technology
working for you.
A word of caution though at this point. At this moment in time, uh, uh, Apple has just released a maverick,
and the current available version of the, ah, technology
accelerator, the accelerator technology
does not work well with Maverick.
Does not play well.
So, hopefully by the time you look at this, um, if you've
got Maverick installed, then the HAXM
technology will have been updated.
If you cannot use the HAXM technology then I encourage
you to play with both the arm emulator and
the
Intel, ah, emulator, to see one, which one is faster for you.
You may find, as I did, ah, that the latest
emulator is a little bit slower than the
earlier ones.
Um, so, if I just, ah, talk about timings for a
moment.
Okay, where is my...
Here it is.
Okay. Ah, if I just talk about, uh, timings for a moment.
Uh, let's see what we've got.
Um, I, I tried with four different instances
here, so
we have the early versions of Android, the, uh, level 10.
Here we go, the API level 10, and I tried
starting up the emulator
in both the arm and Intel, and both of
these took, uh, 30 seconds.
So, a little bit slow, but once you've
started up you can keep uploading
new versions of your app to it and so that's, ah, not, not, not too terrible.
And as you saw, the emulator was, was, was, ah, useful.
On further, more modern operating system, ah,
ah, things are a little bit slow without the
accelerator, so the, the ARM one was, ah,
75 seconds. [pause]
The Intel
was 135
seconds.
And, very slow.
So almost, ah, unusable.
Um, so if you don't have, uh, accelerator
technology, you're going to, to find it an
extremely frustrating, ah, experience to try to
use the latest Intel, ah, ah, ah, emulator.
Right.
So let's see what happens if we, ah, do install the, the technology accelerator.
All right. So, that's, out of this.
Right, how do we do that?
Well, a reminder that we used the SDK
manager.
And, ah, this tool allows us to configure which compartments we have, ah, locally.
So let me, just look at the things I've
got installed.
And you'll see underneath the extras, ah, I
have the Intel x86 Emulator Accelerator or
HAXM.
This, um, only, ah, accelerates the Intel images, not the arm images.
And its revision is, ah, revision three, so if
you're looking at revisions four,
maybe that will be working, ah, well with, ah, Maverick.
Okay, so, l-let's go and have a look at
that.
We've downloaded it, we've installed it,
according to this, but
actually we haven't yet run it, so I need
to go
and look at the SDK here. So we go into
Extras and Intel,
and here is the hardware accelerated
execution manager.
And on a Mac, we have a disk image file.
Let's open this.
You'll have a similar file in Windows.
And, ah, notice that even though, ah,
Android thinks it's version 3, Intel calls
this, ah, version 1.0.6.
So let's open this and just run through
the installation procedure.
Ah, here's a surprise.
We have to make a choice about how much memory to give the acceleration.
Ah, my machine has eight gigabytes.
And, I need some of that obviously for
the operating system, some of that for
Eclipse.
Ah, I'm going to have to put aside some of it, ah,
every time I want to run these hardware
accelerated managers.
The total amount I'm going to put aside is
for all emulators that are running at any
one time.
Now normally I just have one emulator
running.
Ah, what I found is with a emulator the
Nexus 4 is that I
can ump down the actual amount of RAM I
give it, say, from
1900 to about 1500, ah, and then that
comfortably fits inside, um, the Intel limit
here
that I'm going to give the accelerator of
say about two gigabytes or 2048 megabytes.
Um, so this memory allocation, I mean I'm
choosing
to take away from the best of my system.
So you have to try and find a, strike a
balance, with,
with what memory have on, ah, your, your
laptop, or your, o-or your system
so  that you have enough memory to run Eclipse. And the, the, other tools.
Um, so ideally you have at least, uh, a four
gigabyte machine.
Right, so let's go with 2048.
If you, um, decide
to play with this value, all you need to
do is, uh, run this, um, installer
again.
And then you can, ah, change the, ah, the amount of
memory that you've given the accelerator.
Okay, so that's installing.
Ah, it's not going to take five minutes; it's
going to be quicker than that.
And, let's, um,
go back to here.
Right, I should mention how we, we, we, ah, close our emulators.
You could click the power button but that
doesn't actually, ah, stop them.
It's, ah, it's easier to turn them off,
just close them.
Okay, right, so how's the Installer doing?
Right, once this is installed, ah, we're going to try, ah, running one of the emulators
again just to see what kind of speed-up we get here.
Okay, I need clips.
And go to my Android Virtual Device
Manager.
Ah, let's start the Intel at level 10. Launch. [pause] It's working
and the emulator is running in fast vert
mode, ah, so now
we should, ah, see an emulator that is, ah, fairly speedy.
Here we go. And, uh, uh, uh, almost a joy to, to, to develop one.
Okay, so that's, uh, everything we're going to say at this point. I'm
going to f-finally mention that you'll
probably run into an issue or two.
Ah, maybe these, uh, this video has become a little
bit out of date, etcetera,
so do be sure to check the, ah, Coursera
discussion groups.
And also if you have a specific problem, ah, try to find out
as much as you can about your system or
the error message,
and then become a detective.
Use Google, use discussion groups,
etcetera to perhaps try and
find someone that's had, run into a
similar problem as you,
and see how they solved it.
Right.
That's it for now. Uh, time for you to,
ah, play with your emulators and find out what works on your system.
Bye.